# Matthew Shannon

Palo Alto, California, USA 94301

🛮 (+1) 650-670-5926 | 🗷 matthew.j.shannon@gmail.com | 🌴 www.astrochem.org/bios/shannon.php | 🖸 mattjshannon | 🛅 mattjshannon

# Summary\_

I am an astrophysicist and scientific researcher at NASA with 7 years experience analyzing and interpreting scientific datasets, communicating key results to audiences, and working in a team environment. I program primarily in Python, utilizing statistical and machine learning methods, with additional skills in IDL, R, LaTeX and BASH. I am looking to transition into a more practical data-driven role, wherein I can utilize my love for learning and problem solving in real-world applications.

## Education

Ph.D. Astronomy Ontario, Canada

WESTERN UNIVERSITY 2012 - 2016

Awards: (x4) Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology; Graduate Student Teaching Award

M.Sc. Astronomy Ontario, Canada

WESTERN UNIVERSITY 2011 - 2012

Awards: Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology

#### **B.Sc. Honours Physics and Astronomy**

British Columbia, Canada

University of Victoria 2007 - 2011

Awards: Miranda Ward Physics Scholarship; Don Ingham Memorial Scholarship; Physics and Astronomy Co-op Student of the Year

# Work Experience\_

#### **NASA/Universities Space Research Association**

Moffett Field, CA 2017 - PRESENT

NASA Postdoctoral Program Fellow

- · Responsible for helping further the development, exposure and scientific utility of a high-profile NASA database.
- Co-developed and presented an astronomical Python software tool at the SciPy 2018 conference in Texas, in the form of a peer-reviewed conference proceeding and a technical poster.
- Prepared two scientific articles for publication through collaboration with a team of seven local and international scientists.
- Attended a two-week statistical/computer learning workshop at Penn State, providing the foundation for a new machine learning project currently in progress.

Western University Ontario, Canada

POSTGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

2016 - 2017

• Worked with a diverse team of junior and senior scientists, both domestic and international, leading to the publication of a scientific article.

Western University Ontario, Canada

GRADUATE STUDENT: RESEARCH & TEACHING

2011 - 2016

- Presented my scientific research at five international conferences (three talks, four posters).
- Performed public outreach at five all-ages University events, including two talks.
- Assisted hundreds of undergraduate students as a teaching assistant (nine classes over five years).
- Published three scientific articles in peer-reviewed journals.
- Was awarded desirable observing time on the Subaru Telescope in Hawaii and the NASA airborne science platform in California.

### Skills

Data analysis Quantitative/statistical analysis of multidimensional datasets, fitting/decomposition, visualization, problem solving

Programming Python (Numpy, Scipy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Jupyter Notebook, TensorFlow, Keras, scikit-learn, iPython, Seaborn, Travis),

IDL, LaTeX, BASH, R, SQL

**Software** OS X, Windows, Linux, Conda, Git/GitHub, Overleaf, Office, Illustrator, Sublime Text

**Writing** I have authored (4) and refereed (1) publications in peer-reviewed scientific journals.

**Management** Proficient at planning, prioritizing work; emphasis on breaking down long-term goals into tractable tasks; able to work

on unsupervised projects through personal initiative, and as part of a team.

**Communication** As a teaching assistant for nine undergraduate physics and astronomy courses, I have taught, tutored and assisted

hundreds of students. I have presented science concepts to the general public at five outreach events, in addition to nine

academic presentations at five international conferences.

**Collaboration** I frequently work with research groups, both small and large, domestic and international, to find ways to best work

towards common goals, utilizing our individual strengths.